foreign
[Music]
s are intended to prevent further facial
photo aging but can't dramatically
reverse damage presently visible whereas
topical retinoids are the most important
drug class to reverse the signs of aging
also known as all trans retinoic acid
tretinoin sold under a variety of Brands
including Retin-A is a prescriptionally
topical form of vitamin A that can
visibly improve mild to moderate photo
damage including fine and coarse
wrinkles freckles other pigmentation
improve overall skin texture after
months of daily use
this is accompanied by a restoration of
collagen formation skin biopsy taken
before and after 10 to 12 months of
tretinoin versus placebo found that
while skin collagen formation dropped 14
of the control group it Rose 80 in the
retinoic acid group
the downsides are the side effects so
common they have their own name retinoid
reaction plaguing a high proportion of
patients including redness stinging
burning itching and peeling ironically
the constant irritation may be a causal
mechanism constantly forcing the skin to
renew the adverse effects do tend to
improve over time after Peak after about
two weeks of daily use and you can
minimize the irritation by starting at a
lower concentration for example 0.025
instead of 0.1 percent and slowly
ramping up from applying at first twice
a week for a few weeks then to every
other night for a few more weeks before
finally advancing to Nightly application
as tolerated
give that a small amount is systemically
absorbed out of an abundance of caution
women of child bearing capacity may want
to steer clear given the severe birth
defects caused by a similar drug
isotrotinoin sold formally as the acne
drug Accutane
there are gentler less potent
over-the-counter topical retinoids
retinol retinol and retinal there's
retinal acetate retinal palmitate
propionate retinol retinaldehyde once
absorbed into your skin your body can
convert them into small amounts of
retinoic acid however data is limited on
these non-prescription retinoids the
results of clinical trials on the
retinal Esters have been routinely
disappointing even 48 weeks of daily use
has found to be ineffective for reducing
wrinkles compared to placebo
retinaldehyde and retinol however hold
some promise there was a 48-week
head-to-head trial of retinaldehyde
versus retinoic Acid versus placebo now
retinoids can be so irritating that's
hard to Blind participants as to whether
or not they're in the control group so
objective measures that may be less
susceptible to Placebo effects are
especially important so what they did is
make silicone molds of the crow's feet
wrinkles around the eyes of the
participants before and after being
randomized to one of those three groups
and then analyze scans of the molds
using high resolution Digital Image
processing
the retinal aldehyde group showed a
similar reduction in fine lines and
wrinkles as the retinol Castle group
with less irritation only 23 of the
retinaldehyde group experience skin
irritation compared to 71 in the
retinoic acid group versus four percent
in the placebo cream group
of all the non-profession retinoid
options retinol may be the preferred
choice though it causes even less
irritation than retinaldehyde in
significantly different than Placebo and
randomized double blind signal control
trial found that 52 weeks of use
improved crow's feet Fine Lines by 44
and modeled pigmentation by 84 percent
but tretinoin renoric acid has by far
the most robust track record of efficacy
so why not just ask your doctor for a
prescription
because long-term topical tretinoin use
may increase your risk of an even more
stinging side effect death
topical tretinoin therapy and all-cause
mortality the Veterans Affairs topical
tretinoin chemo prevention trial was to
be a six-year randomized controlled
trial to see if it could help prevent
skin cancer but the trial had to be
stopped early because significantly more
people were dying in the retinoic acid
group than the placebo cream group
at the time the study was halted 19 of
the subjects in the tretinoin group had
died compared to 14 in the placebo group
between one to eight percent of
topically Applied retinoic acid is
absorbed into the bloodstream could it
be killing people oh we don't know if
the increase in deaths was a statistical
fluke that happened by chance or a real
biological effect the probability that
we'd see such a discrepancy just by
chance is about one in a hundred
tretinoin continues to be banned in
Europe for cosmetic purposes
foreign